<!-- Note: Under construction; not ready for prime time -->
<shavian title="Pitman on Shavian">
<crumb href=".">&lt;cite&gt;Androcles&lt;/cite&gt;</crumb>
<text a="latn" only="1">
<p>Here is Shaw's alphabet. It has been proved that those who wish to read it can do so after only a few hours of concentrated deciphering.</p>

<p>Why should anyone wish to use it? And why should there be any departure from the familiar forms of the Roman alphabet in which English is printed and written?</p>

<p>You will notice from the comparisons that Shaw's alphabet is both more legible and one-third more economical in space than traditional printing, and this should lead to a great increase in reading speed. The characters themselves are very distinct. To prove them more legible, open the book and hold it upside down in front of a mirror. Both mirrored pages will thus become equally unfamiliar. Keep the back of the book pressed against your lips, and advance towards the mirror until you are able to see individual characters clearly enough to be able to copy them. Note that the Shaw characters are clearly seen at a greater distance.</p>

<p>The economy in space and greater simplicity of characters ought also to increase the speed and ease of writing -- even more than it does the ease of reading. Many of the characters easily join into pairs and trios to form syllables which recur frequently in English words; the sounds of the language are completely characterized, thus permitting abbreviation with great reliability. Shaw found traditional script too laborious, and Pitman's shorthand too economical. Though at this time we can only guess, it is probable that an abbreviated handwriting speed of 60-100 words a minute, with complete reliability of reading, will be possible for those who attain 'automatic' facility with Shaw's alphabet. In other words, reading may be 50-75 per cent, and writing 80-100 per cent faster, and even 200-300 per cent, by using simple abbreviations.</p>

<p>Shaw insisted that, unless his alphabet were to offer the substantial advantages he himself desired, there would be no reason for adding to the existing media of communication, which include: typewriting, shorthand, morse, semaphore, and braille, in addition to the Roman alphabet which is itself represented by three quite different sets of signs (as in 'alphabet', 'alphabet', and 'alphabet').  The Key on page 151 (duplicated on the bookmark) will enable you to achieve the beginnings of skill and the satisfaction of success within three or four hours. Although this means starting from scratch, remember that Isaac Pitman, whose shorthand Shaw used for all his writings, also did so with a system offering the same advantages as Shaw's alphabet: that is, the saving of time, effort, and money.</p>

<p>Shaw did not want you and me to abandon the Roman alphabet. The long-established Roman figures (I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, VIII, IX) remain even after the Arabic figures (the newer and handier 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9) have found favour. We now use both, with greater convenience. The new figures were not imposed, nor the old supplanted. Similarly, Shaw believed, uses would be found for a new and handier alphabet without abandoning the old one.</p>

<p>If those who tried it found it advantageous, they would use it, and by their example it would gain what following it deserved. If its benefits were substantial enough, it would spread and establish itself through merit –- as Arabic numerals did despite the then complete satisfaction with Roman numerals.</p>

<p>Utilitarian advantage is thus the principle governing the new alphabet. Shaw was unique in pointing out that substantial economy could be attained only<ul type="a"><li>if the designer were to depart from a system evolved by the Romans 2,000 years ago for carving their public notices in stone;</li><li>if a single set of alphabetical characters were used -- abolishing the different look of words in capitals, small letters, and linked handwritten letters; and (c) if each distinct sound of the language were spelt with its own unvarying character.</li></ul></p>

<p>These three factors in designing, taken together, made a non-Roman alphabet essential. Of course, there is nothing revolutionary in that. There are hundreds of non-Roman alphabets -- and there are several variations within the Roman alphabet, e.g.</p>

<table>
<tr><th rowspan="3">Roman variations</th><td style="text-transform: uppercase">here is a sentence</td></tr>
<tr><td>here is a sentence</td></tr>
<tr><td style="font-family: cursive">here is a sentence</td></tr>
<tr><td>Greek</td><td>here is a sentence</td></tr>
<tr><td>Russian</td><td>here is a sentence</td></tr>
</table>

<p>Thus these four English words may already be represented in a number of existing alphabets. Those who know Greek and English, Russian and English, etc., will have no difficulty in reading that sentence immediately in as many alphabets as they know -- and it is considered at school that once a child has learned his A, B, C, D he is well placed to learn also his a, b, c, d, his a, b, c, d, his (Greek), and his (Russian).</p>

<p>Only a few hours will be needed to persuade you that the new alphabet has the potential advantages Shaw intended for it. At first you will read and write it in a plodding childlike way, as you once did Roman. Much more rapidly than a child's, your familiarity and ease will grow, until the use of Shaw's alphabet becomes as natural and automatic as your use of Roman -- but faster.</p>

<p>In personal and intimate writing the forty-eight (40+8) characters of the Shaw alphabet may faithfully portray the pronunciation of the individual; but, as Shaw pointed out, too eccentric a dialect may hamper, and even destroy, effective communication. He considered that, though there was no need to standardize writing if not intended for publication, there was every need for conformity in print; standard spellings being particularly desirable when that print is intended for circulation throughout the English-speaking world.</p>

<p>In his Will, Shaw specified just such a standardization for this play. He laid down for it a 'pronunciation to resemble that recorded of His Majesty our late King George V and sometimes described as Northern English'. He was an expert in stage direction and, so it may be supposed, considered this pronunciation to be the best basis for comprehension with acceptability in reading as he had found it to be in speech from the stage.</p>

<p>But by all means write as you think fit, and leave experts to standardize printers' spelling.</p>

<p>This book costs very little. Get your friends to buy one and to learn the alphabet so that you can write to one another -- or, if you become so skilled that you no longer need to 'keep your eye in', give it away.</p>

<p>JAMES PITMAN<br />
House of Commons<br />
London<br />
1962</p>
</text>
</shavian>

